Where's Papa going with that axe? said Fern to her mother as they were setting
the table for breakfast. Out to the hog house, replied Mrs. Arable. Some pigs
were born last night. I don't see why he needs an axe, continued Fern, who was
only eight. Well, said her mother. One of the pigs is a runt. It's very small
and weak, and it'll never amount to anything. So, your father has decided to do away with it.
Do away with it? Shrieked Fern. You mean kill it? Just because it's smaller than
the others? Mrs. Darable put a picture of cream on the table. "Don't yell,
Fern," she said. "Your father is right.
The pig would probably die anyway." Fern pushed a chair out of the way and ran
outdoors. The grass was wet and the earth smelled of springtime.
Fern's sneakers were sping by the time she caught up with her father.
"Please don't kill it," she sobbed.
"It's unfair." Mr. Parable stopped walking. "Fern," he said gently. "You
will have to learn to control yourself."
"Control myself?" yelled Fern. "This is a matter of life and death, and you talk
about controlling myself."
Tears ran down her cheeks, and she took hold of the axe and tried to pull it out
of her father's hand.
"Fern," said Mr. Arable. I know more about raising a litter of pigs than you
do. A weakling makes trouble. Now run along. But it's unfair, cried Fern. The
pig couldn't help being born small, could it? If I had been very small at
birth, would you have killed me?
Mr. Arable smiled.
Certainly not, he said, looking down at his daughter with love. But this is
different. A little girl is one thing. A little runty pig is another. I see no
difference, replied Fern, still hanging on to the axe. This is the most terrible
case of injustice I ever heard of. A queer look came over John Arabel's face.
He seemed almost ready to cry himself.
"All right," he said. "You go back to the house, and I'll bring the runt when
I come in. I'll let you start it on a bottle like a baby. Then you'll see what
trouble a pig can be.
When Mr. Arable returned to the house half an hour later, he carried a carton
under his arm. Fern was upstairs changing her sneakers. The kitchen table
was set for breakfast, and the room smelled of coffee, bacon, damp plaster,
and wood smoke from the stove. Put it on her chair, said Mrs. Arable. Mr. Arable
set the carton down at Fern's place.
Then he walked to the sink and washed his hands and dried them on the roller towel.
Fern came slowly down the stairs. Her eyes were red from crying.
As she approached her chair, the carton wobbled and there was a scratching noise.
Fern looked at her father. Then she lifted the lid of the carton. There
inside, looking up at her, was the newborn pig. It was a white one. The
morning light shone through its ears, turning them pink. "He's yours," said
Mr. Arable, saved from an untimely death. "And may the good Lord forgive me
for this foolishness."
Fern couldn't take her eyes off the tiny pig. Oh," she whispered. "Oh, look at
him. He's absolutely perfect." She closed the carton carefully. First, she
kissed her father. Then, she kissed her mother. Then, she opened the lid again,
lifted the pig out, and held it against her cheek. At this moment, her brother
Avery came into the room.
Avery was 10. He was heavily armed, an air rifle in one hand, a wooden dagger
in the other. What's that? He demanded.
What's Fern got? She's got a guest for breakfast, said Mrs. Arable. Wash your
hands and face, Avery.
Let's see it, said Avery, setting his gun down. You called that miserable
thing a pig. That's a fine specimen of a pig. It's no bigger than a white rat.
Wash up and eat your breakfast, Avery, said his mother. The school bus will be
along in half an hour. Can I have a pig, too, Pop? asked Avery.
No, I only distribute pigs to early risers, said Mr. Arable. Fern was up a
daylight trying to rid the world of injustice.
As a result, she now has a pig. A small one to be sure, but nevertheless a pig.
It just shows what can happen if a person gets out of bed promptly. Let's eat.
But Fern couldn't eat until her pig had had a drink of milk. Mrs. Arable found a
baby's nursing bottle and a rubber nipple. She poured warm milk into the
bottle, fitted the nipple over the top, and handed it to Fern. Give him his
breakfast, she said. A minute later, Fern was seated on the floor in the
corner of the kitchen with her infant between her knees, teaching it to suck
from the bottle. The pig, although tiny, had a good appetite and caught on quickly.
The school bus honked from the road.
"Run," commanded Mrs. Arable, taking the pig from Fern and slipping a donut into
her hand. Avery grabbed his gun and another donut. The children ran out to
the road and climbed into the bus. Fern took no notice of the others in the bus.
She just sat and stared out of the window, thinking what a blissful world
it was, and how lucky she was to have entire charge of a pig.
By the time the bus reached school, Fern had named her pet, selecting the most
beautiful name she could think of. "Its name is Wilbur," she whispered to
herself. She was still thinking about the pig when the teacher said, "Fern,
what is the capital of Pennsylvania?"
"Wilbur," replied Fern dreily. The pupils giggled.
Fern blushed.
Chapter 2.
Wilbur.
[Music]